# Maria Korochkina, PhD

I am a cognitive neuroscientist studying language and memory, with **advanced technical skills** in data analysis and statistics. I have a strong commitment to **open science** and am actively involved in promoting transparency and reproducibility in research. I am passionate about **making research accessible** to the wider community and strive to **engage diverse voices in research** to drive meaningful societal change.

# **Education and qualifications**

- PhD in Cognitive Science

  Joint degree from Macquarie University (Australia) and Universities of Potsdam (Germany),

  Newcastle upon Tyne (UK), Groningen (Netherlands), Trento (Italy), IDEALAB PhD programme

  2021 Badged Instructor, The Carpentries

  2015 − 2018 MSc in Experimental and Clinical Linguistics

  University of Potsdam, Germany, IECL programme

  2010 − 2015 BA & MA in Philology
- Lomonosov Moscow State University, Russia

# o6/2022 – ongoing o2/2020 – o6/2022 o7/2016 – o8/2018 ■ Postdoctoral Research Fellow, Rastle Lab, Royal Holloway, University of London, UK Academic Tutor, Macquarie University, Australia Research Assistant, NOLA Lab & Vasishth Lab, University of Potsdam, Germany

# Teaching and educating

**Academic employment** 

10/07/2024	Invited speaker, 31st annual meeting of the Society for the Scientific Study of Reading Workshop "Opening up Open Science: Nuts and Bolts for Beginners"  Pre-registration & Open Materials: The What, Why, & How
10/06/2024	■ Invited speaker, Festival of Research, Royal Holloway, University of London ReproducibiliTea journal club: Fostering open science and reproducible research
27/03/2023	Workshop instructor, Royal Holloway, University of London Bayesian Linear Mixed Effects and Distributional Regression models with brms
7/11/2022 – ongoing	■ Instructor, ReproducibiliTea journal club, Royal Holloway, University of London
02/2020 - 06/2022	Academic Tutor, Macquarie University Session 1, 2021 & 2022: Design and Statistics III Session 2, 2020 & 2021: Design and Statistics II Session 2, 2020 & 2021: Acquired Speech and Language Disorders Session 1, 2020: Exp Design and Data Analysis for the Cognitive and Brain Sciences
18/02/2021	Workshop instructor, Macquarie University Data analysis using (generalised) linear mixed effects models in R
21-25/09/2020	■ Co-instructor, Introduction to R Software Carpentry workshop, Macquarie University

#### **Publications**

Pre-registrations, data, materials, analysis code, and pre-prints for all papers are available on OSF (https://osf.io/zf8px/).

#### Pre-prints under review

**Korochkina**, **M.**, & Rastle, K. (2024a). The vocabulary barrier in the General Certificate of Secondary Education (GCSE) in English Literature [Pre-print]. https://doi.org/10.31219/osf.io/vg8c3

#### Peer-reviewed

- Crawford, M., Raheel, N., **Korochkina**, **M.**, & Rastle, K. (In press). Inadequate foundational decoding skills constrain global literacy goals for pupils in low- and middle-income countries. *Nature Human Behaviour*. https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/2qxm9
- Korochkina, M., Marelli, M., Brysbaert, M., & Rastle, K. (2024). The Children and Young People's Books Lexicon (CYP-LEX): A large-scale lexical database of books read by children and young people in the United Kingdom [Published online ahead of print]. *Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology*. https://doi.org/10.1177/17470218241229694
- **Korochkina**, M., Nickels, L., & Bürki, A. (2024). What can we learn about integration of novel words into semantic memory from automatic semantic priming? *Language, Cognition, and Neuroscience*, *39*(4), 455–488. https://doi.org/10.1080/23273798.2024.2328586
- Lombard, A., Ulicheva, A., **Korochkina**, **M.**, & Rastle, K. (2024). The regularity of polysemy patterns in the mind: Computational and experimental data. *GLOSSA Psycholinguistics*, 3(1), 3, 1–24. https://doi.org/10.5070/G60111327
- **Korochkina**, **M.**, Sowman, P., Nickels, L., & Bürki, A. (2023). Neural correlates of encoding in novel word learning. *Collabra: Psychology*, *9*(1), 57525. https://doi.org/10.1525/collabra.57525
- **Korochkina**, **M.**, Bürki, A., & Nickels, L. (2021). Apples and oranges: How does learning context affect novel word learning? *Journal of Memory and Language*, 120, 104246. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jml.2021.104246

#### **Theses**

**Korochkina**, M. (2022a). Learning of new words: Behavioural and electrophysiological correlates of encoding and integration [PhD thesis]. Macquarie University. https://doi.org/10.25949/23707128.v1

#### Outreach contributions

#### **Publications**

- (1) Korochkina, M., & Rastle, K. (2024b). What makes GCSE English Literature so hard for students?, Tes Magazine. https://www.tes.com/magazine/teaching-learning/secondary/what-makes-gcse-english-lit-so-hard-students
- **Korochkina**, **M.**, & Rastle, K. (2024c). What words do children encounter when they read for pleasure? [Also available on https://www.rastlelab.com/post/what-words-do-children-encounter-when-they-read-for-pleasure], Nomanis, Issue 27. https://www.nomanis.com.au/blog/issue-17-june-2024

#### **Talks**

- **Korochkina**, M. (2024d, June). What does it take to read and understand the GCSE English Literature texts? Working Together: Research and Practice event 2024, The South East Research Network for Schools, Egham, UK. https://www.royalholloway.ac.uk/research-and-teaching/departments-and-schools/psychology/research/serns/serns-events/2024/
- **Korochkina**, **M.**, & Rastle, K. (2024d, September). Words in books: A challenge, a blessing, or both? (Invited talk). ResearchED National Conference, London, UK. <a href="https://researched.org.uk/event/researched-national-conference-2024/">https://researched.org.uk/event/researched-national-conference-2024/</a>

# Academic and administrative service

Peer-review Reviewer for Psychonomic Bulletin & Review; Behavior Research Methods; Journal of Memory and Language; Language, Cognition, & Neuroscience; Advances in Cognitive Psychology; Language and Speech; Psychology & Neuroscience, Applied Psycholinguistics

Equality, diversity, & inclusion Postdoc representative in a successful bid for the Athena Swan Silver award Royal Holloway, University of London

## Awards and funding

2023	Student Researcher Credibility Prize, The British Neuroscience Association
	Read the media announcement here.
2021	Funding award for an 8-week Instructor Training with The Carpentries, Macquarie University
2020	Postgraduate Research Fund, Macquarie University
2019-2022	■ International Research Excellence PhD Scholarship, Macquarie University

2019 Conference travel & participant recruitment awards, University of Potsdam

2018–2019 **PhD Scholarship**, University of Potsdam

2012 & 2014 Student exchange awards, University of Vienna, Austria

# **Scientific societies**

- The British Neuroscience Association
- The Experimental Psychology Society
- Society for the Scientific Study of Reading
- The European Society for Cognitive Psychology
- The Psychonomic Society

#### Skills

Experimental techniques Behavioural, eye-tracking, fNIRS, EEG Corpus linguistics, computational modelling

Programming languages & software MATLAB, Python, R, Stan, Presentation Neurobehavioural Systems Stata, HTML, OpenSesame, Languages & Stata, HTML, OpenSesame, L

Languages English, German, Russian, Swedish, Icelandic (beginner)
British Sign Language (beginner)

#### Conference contributions

Slide decks for all talks and posters are available on my website (https://mariakna.github.io).

#### Selected talks

- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2024b, July). The nature of morphemic regularities in children's literature: What do British children learn about derivational morphology when they read? Talk given at the 31st annual meeting of the Society for the Scientific Study of Reading, Copenhagen, Denmark.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2024c, July). What can children learn about English morphology through book reading? Talk given at the annual meeting of the Experimental Psychology Society, York, UK.

- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2023a, September). *Apples and oranges: How does learning context affect novel word learning?* Talk given at the Contextual Diversity Workshop organised by the Experimental Psychology Society, London, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2023b, January). *Behavioural and electrophysiological markers of integration in novel word learning*. Talk given at the annual meeting of the Experimental Psychology Society, London, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2023c, September). The Children and Young People's Books Lexicon (CYP-LEX): A lexical database of books directed at children and young adults. Talk given at the annual meeting of the European Society for Cognitive Psychology, Porto, Portugal.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2023d, July). The Children and Young People's Books Lexicon (CYP-LEX): How does book language change as children transition into and through adolescence? Talk given at the annual meeting of the Experimental Psychology Society, Swansea, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2023e, September). What do children read as they transition into and through adolescence? Insights from CYP-LEX, a new large-scale lexicon of books for children and young people. Talk given at the annual meeting of the Cognitive and Developmental sections of the British Psychological Society, Bristol, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2021, October). Behavioural and electrophysiological markers of integration in novel word learning. Talk given at the annual meeting of the Society for the Neurobiology of Language, online attendance.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2020a, October). *A behavioural and electrophysiological investigation of novel word learning*. Talk given at the Words in the World conference, online attendance.

#### **Posters**

- Korochkina, M. (2024a, November). Learning in the wild: What can children learn about morphemic statistical regularities through reading? Poster to be presented at the 65<sup>th</sup> annual meeting of the Psychonomic Society, New York City, USA.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2022b, September). Neural correlates of encoding in learning of novel names for novel concepts. Poster presented at the Architectures & Mechanisms for Language Processing conference, York, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2020b, November). *Behavioural and electrophysiological markers of integration in novel word learning*. Poster presented at the 61<sup>st</sup> annual meeting of the Psychonomic Society, online attendance.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2019a, September). *The effect of the learning context on novel word learning*. Poster presented at the Architectures & Mechanisms for Language Processing conference, Moscow, Russia.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2019b, September). *Semantic integration of new vocabulary: Does learning context matter?*Poster presented at the annual meeting of the European Society for Cognitive Psychology, Tenerife, Spain.

# Further training and development

- Introduction to Natural Language Processing in Python
  DataCamp
  - The 6<sup>th</sup> Summer School on Statistical Methods for Linguistics and Psychology Bayesian Advanced Track University of Potsdam
- - MATLAB Fundamentals
    A MathWorks workshop, Macquarie University

# Further training and development (continued)

# **■ Python Basics for Data Science** *edX*

## ■ Understanding the Brain: The Neurobiology of Everyday Life

MOOC, University of Chicago

#### 2019 Australasian Magnetoencephalography (WAM)

Workshop on the Neurocognitive clinical applications of MEG: Present and future Macquarie University

#### **■** Introduction to Python

Software Carpentry Workshop, Macquarie University

#### ■ The 3<sup>rd</sup> Summer School on Statistical Methods for Linguistics and Psychology

Bayesian Advanced Track University of Potsdam

#### 2018 Advanced Methods: Bayesian Statistics with R

Workshop, University of Potsdam

#### 2017 NIRS-Workshop

NIRx Medizintechnik GmbH, Berlin

#### 2016 NIRS-Workshop

NIRx Medizintechnik GmbH, Berlin

#### ■ Standardised Tests of Cognitive and Language Development in Children

Workshop, University of Potsdam